Amen.
I'd like to start by reading a short section of a manuscript I've been working on for about a year now.
And it's talking about this whole seasons of formation that we've been walking through.
And it's titled The Next Season.
You do know that human nature is to assume that the state you are in will be perpetual.
That if I'm just like bummed, it's never going to be better.
Or if I'm doing well, I've got to figure it out now.
And the reality is that there's usually a next season.
Today there's a lot of talk about resilience.
Quote, psychologists define resilience as the process of adapting well in the face of adversity, trauma, tragedy, threats, or significant sources of stress.
Seasons of formation are passive ways that God builds resilience into his children.
Just as humans, they naturally need emotional times of stress and repair, activity and rest, intensity and relaxation to build healthy resilience, so too, in our spiritual development.
God trains us in holiness, using various seasons at varying times.
Typically, believers begin their journey in a season of delight and enter some of their most challenging times as they mature.
But it would be a mistake to view the seasons as we've presented them as linear.
God does not necessarily lead his children through seasons in the order that we've delivered them.
He is sovereign.
Nor should every season necessarily be viewed as God's scent.
Times of great physical, financial, or relational difficulty that thrust us into a hard life.
Now, God may, in those adverse times, choose to show or hide his presence.
And in doing so, change the season.
But he's not likely the author of your sickness or your financial hardship or your strained relationships.
Those things may be the result of your activity, someone else's activity, or totally unconnected to any particular activity.
Regardless, in the theology of seasons, it doesn't matter.
God's promise is to use whatever season you are in, whatever season you are in, regardless of why you are there, to make you more like Jesus.
However you arrived in the desert, did God allure you there?
Did you blindly wander in?
Did it just descend violently upon you?
Avoid the why question.
Instead, remember to focus on the how and the what.
The important formational questions that will help fill your well with living water.
So, I have to be honest.
Last week was actually hard for me to preach.
And the rest of that day, I was like in a funk.
I couldn't do anything.
I just felt, blah!
And I think it's because it is hard to tell people that sometimes God, sometimes he brings us into the darkness.
When he chooses to hide himself, he does that.
And those are hard things to think about.
But I thought, man, what a shame to leave you with that thought on seasons.
So today, I want to talk about the next season.
You'll notice I don't have a suit coat on.
I have a nice, brightly colored shirt on.
I want to be a little more upbeat.
Because the reality is that the place you find yourself in today, God has a plan to make things better for you.
He just does.
It's his plan.
You know, a coach doesn't exhaust you to exhaust you.
But rather, so you don't exhaust so quickly the next time you do something.
My mom was a manners Nazi.
Sorry, mom.
I know you're watching.
Get your elbows off the table.
Put your napkin on your lap.
Don't chew with your mouth open.
Don't use that fork.
Don't try to kill the food on your plate, Matt.
Eat it.
And I have to be honest, it was rather annoying at the time.
In fact, it got so annoying at the time, even my father would say,
Joan, let up on him a little bit.
But I got to tell you today, I mean, I'll go to like a fancy meal.
And you ever been at one of those meals and you're all sitting around the table and there's like, you know, 54 things to use in front of you?
And everyone's waiting for someone else to pick up the first thing because no one's sure which one you should pick up.
It's really nice that my mom walked me through all of that stuff.
Did she want me to feel miserable?
No.
But she was prepping me for something.
Tomorrow, I have to go to, and I use the word purposely, forgive me if you're a dentist, I have to go to the dentist.
They put two crowns in my mouth last week and there needs to be some adjusting.
But no one in their right mind goes to the dentist because they like fingers or clamps or picks or drills in their mouth.
But let me tell you, you have a bad toothache and you can't wait to get to the dentist.
Often the thing, I've said it this way before, all of God's good things don't feel good at the time.
But what's critical for us is to realize that in the seasons of formation, this is God's activity in your heart,
answering your prayer to be made more like Jesus, that in all of it, his goal for you is good.
Regardless of how it feels.
I'm going to read a couple passages as we go through and we'll end with that passage.
By the way, I loved your response today.
Donovan, you did a nice job reading the Scriptures.
I like when people read Scriptures with some thought and meaning.
But it's one of the first times in a while that I've seen a group of people applaud the Scriptures.
That's awesome.
We should more often applaud the Scriptures.
Paul is writing.
It's in Philippians.
It's a passage that most of you are probably familiar with.
It's chapter 3.
It's going to begin in verse 10.
He says, I want to know Christ.
I mean, this is the guy who's planting all the churches.
This is the guy who got knocked down on the road to Damascus.
This is the guy who got specifically called audibly by name.
Rebuked in the call, but called nonetheless.
Rebuked in the call, but God healed that.
Not all of God's good things feel good at the time.
But in the midst of that, he's crying out, but I want to know him.
I think Paul knew him.
And yet there's something intimate in this word know.
In fact, the word know is often in the Scriptures used for incredible intimacy.
Adam knew Eve, and the result was children.
But there is this intimacy in knowing.
He says, I want to know Christ.
And then here's what he says.
Yes, to know the power of the resurrection.
How many of you want that?
Okay, four of you.
Ryan, we need to preach on that next week.
How many of you want to know the power of his resurrection?
How about the fellowship of his sufferings?
So here's a truth you can take to the bank.
There is never, ever, ever a resurrection that's not preceded with a death.
Paul was not saying, oh, I want to suffer.
He wasn't saying, oh, yeah, I like suffering.
I mean, there have been some movements in the church that have gone sideways.
And they've raised up suffering.
And they've caused it to themselves like somehow it's a virtue in and of itself.
No.
But Paul realized that if I'm going to know the power of his resurrection,
I need to be willing to be intimate with the fellowship of his sufferings.
The koinonia.
The common union.
The fellowship of his sufferings.
Why?
Because, man, I want to know Christ.
I want the power of the resurrection.
And the fellowship of his sufferings.
Becoming like him in his death.
And so, somehow, attaining to the resurrection of the dead.
He's not fearful of his future salvation.
But he wants the power of the resurrection.
He wants the fullness of what God.
In fact, he goes on to say, not that I've already grabbed the hold of God.
For what he's grabbed the hold of me.
But I press.
Because I want to get a hold of everything that God has.
I don't know about you.
But I think if I had done everything Paul did, I'd be like, yeah, okay, I'm doing pretty good.
He's like, no, I want to grab.
I want to grab.
So, I'm going to make a statement.
And then I'm going to try to defend the statement through the use of Scripture.
Some great Christian thinkers.
Some people who are smarter than me.
And we'll end with that passage in John where Jesus talks about.
It's really his talk about the resurrection.
He's talking about his own death and resurrection in that John passage that we applauded for.
The disciples were clueless.
And he's trying to get it through to them.
Trying to explain it to them.
So, here's the statement I want to make.
The end goal of God's seasons of formation in your life is your enjoyment.
Okay, let me read a passage for you if I can.
Oh, it's great.
I transferred my notes this morning and I didn't put the passage down.
I'll give you the quote.
It's in Timothy.
It's 1 Timothy 6 somewhere.
You know, by the way, you know, Paul would often say he'd quote the Old Testament.
And do you know what he'd say when he'd quote it?
It's written somewhere.
Yeah.
So, here it is.
And I'll get it for you later if you want.
I have it in my book bag somewhere.
But it's in 1 Timothy 6.
He tells those who are rich to, quote,
put their hope in God,
who richly provides us with everything for our enjoyment.
Did you hear what that said?
Put your hope in God,
who richly provides us with everything for our enjoyment.
Now, I understand that you can interpret that two different ways.
You can say that everything you need to enjoy life,
to enjoy stuff,
is provided by God.
But I tend to take it the more extreme way,
the bigger way,
that everything God provides you with
is intended to an end result of full life.
That I've come to give you life and that more abundantly.
It's the fellowship,
not just of his sufferings,
but the power of his resurrection.
Because every resurrection starts with a death.
It's where it begins.
Jesus said,
for the joy set before him,
he what?
He endured the cross.
I mean,
Jesus wasn't like,
I can't wait to get to the cross,
Father.
In fact,
I think he said,
is there another way,
Dad?
Do you have any other ideas?
Could we look at some other options here?
In his humanity,
he's like,
but for the joy set before him,
for the power of the resurrection,
he embraced the fellowship of sufferings.
C.S. Lewis made this observation.
He was not just a great writer,
but he was a great observer.
I think what made him such a good articulator of truth
was he just saw things that everyone sees,
but people don't always notice.
He said,
I had never noticed that all enjoyment
spontaneously overflows into praise.
And then picking up on that,
John Piper read the quote,
read actually the article that he wrote,
and he coined a term
that is going to take you to a backseat.
You need to read what he means by it,
but he coined a term,
Christian hedonism.
Hedonism is just kind of our own focus
on our own pleasure.
And he talked about Christian hedonism,
that there is an ultimate goal
that God would get all glory,
that all praise would go to God.
He created us so that we could glorify him.
He created us so that we could praise him.
And in that creation,
he made it so that enjoyment
naturally overflows in the very thing that he wants.
So God desires that you enjoy.
In fact,
so the Westminster Confession was penned by,
well,
the shorter catechism of the Westminster Confession
was penned by Puritan elders.
And they wrote that the chief end of man
is to glorify God and enjoy him forever.
And Piper looks at that in the historical context,
and he says,
well,
actually,
what they meant was not an and.
Because they weren't saying the chief ends,
plural,
but the chief end,
the main purpose for humanity
is not two things,
it's one thing.
It's to glorify God.
And how do you glorify God?
By enjoying him forever.
The chief end,
the prime goal
is that we would glorify God
by enjoying him forever.
I had a good friend,
good mentor,
professor,
passed away a few years ago.
But he would say often,
and you've probably heard me say this before,
and I'll say it often
because I think it's important,
that we misinterpret the Bible
when we think it calls us to die to self.
It calls us to die to selfishness.
God's nuts about yourself.
He's nuts about you.
He loves you.
And in fact,
he loves you in a way
that he wants you to enjoy.
These seasons,
you know,
last week,
I talked about a really hard time.
And if you've walked through it,
you know that
you can't even begin to describe it.
And yet,
even that,
God intended
in your life,
and I would say in my life as well,
to bring about joy.
Maybe not in the moment.
We'll get into that a little farther.
So,
in my writing,
I've passed it out
to a lot of people
that I tell them,
please tell me what's wrong with it.
And then I quote the verse
where, you know,
the wounds of a friend
being a good thing.
And,
darn it,
they take me up on it.
You know?
They tell me,
what's all wrong with it?
But, I mean,
it's been a great journey.
But one of the statements
that a guy that I really respect,
I really love,
he's all in for Jesus.
He's,
all of his life,
he's been all in for Jesus.
And,
and I admitted in my paper
that I didn't understand something,
but I was sharing it.
And he goes,
yeah,
I don't get that either.
That makes no sense at all.
So,
last week,
I talked about
Bernard of Cliveau
and his four levels of love.
Some of you may remember.
Some of you may have been,
like in Hawaii,
in your mind,
I get that.
But,
I had a friend who was,
actually,
the guy who led me to the Lord.
I was preaching one time,
and he's this tall,
big Italian guy
with thick eyebrows.
And while I was preaching,
he was like glaring at me.
And I'm thinking,
I don't know what I did
to offend Mark,
but, you know,
it's true.
I'm gonna,
and when I finished,
afterwards,
I said,
Mark,
I don't know what I said
to offend you.
He goes,
no,
that was great,
man,
I was paying attention.
And I realized
all the other times
he was,
dum dum dum dum dum.
So glares are sometimes good.
With these lights,
I have no idea
if you're glaring at me or not,
so that's even better.
Bernardo Cliveau said
that we start with,
we love ourself for ourself,
and that's the unregenerate person.
And at some point,
we grow,
and we begin to love God
for ourself.
And that's the season of delight
that many of us enter into
when we first get saved.
You know,
I became a Christian
because I've come to give you life
and that more abundantly.
I wanted everything
that life had to be.
I wanted the best of life.
I wanted all that God had for me.
And so I thought,
oh,
okay,
I'll love him.
And it was honestly
somewhat transactional.
And God was willing
to deal with me
at that point.
It's kind of like
your children's obedience
when they're little.
They don't obey you
because they're great moral people.
They obey you
because they like the reward
or they hate the consequence.
And hopefully,
as you help them
take the things
that you give externally
and they internalize it,
they do it because
of the character development
that's being birthed
inside of them.
That's the hopeful piece.
So I think it's fine
that God starts with us
loving him,
knowing that it's going
to benefit me.
But that at some point,
and this was the point
of the desert
and the point
of the dark night
of the soul,
we love God for God.
And for most
of my Christian existence,
I saw that as the pinnacle.
That I want to be like Job.
Now, I don't want
to be like Job,
but I want the end result
of Job.
I don't know that I want
to go through the pathway,
but I want the end result.
I want the power
of the resurrection.
But Bernard said
that there's a fourth level
of love.
And I'll be honest with you,
it made no sense to me.
In fact, I thought
he messed up the order.
And in fact,
I thought when I first read it
that the guy
must have misprinted it.
So I went out
and searched for some other copies
of what Bernard wrote.
The fourth level of love,
as he said,
we learn to love ourselves
for God.
Because really,
Bernard didn't say this,
but the chief end of man
is to glorify God
by enjoying him forever.
It's only been
in the last few years
that I begin to be able
to internalize
this whole concept
that God receives
great glory
when we enjoy.
I was going to save
this quote for the end,
but I'll give it now.
Howard Thurman,
great African-American
thinker, writer, theologian,
said,
don't ask what the world needs.
Ask what makes you come alive
and do it.
Because what the world needs
is people who've come alive.
1 Peter 1.8.
To scattered Jewish believers
struggling in a pagan world.
To people who he describes
in verse 6
as suffering grief
and all kinds of trials.
A tough time,
a tough group of people
struggling
out in their diaspora,
their dispersion.
He says,
though you do not see him now,
you believe in him
and are filled
with an inexpressible
and glorious joy.
So,
I'm going to ask the question.
You don't have to answer.
But,
if you want to,
you can put your hand up.
Are there some things
that your parents did
when you were growing up
that you're really thankful for
and you're like,
I want to model
my parenting after that?
Are there,
mom puts Ryan's hand up.
Yes,
I will.
So,
get on his lap
and hold him down
for this next one.
Are there some things
in your parents'
upbringing of you
that created a commitment
in you
to not repeat that
in your kids?
And,
and in doing that,
are you now seeing
some of the fruit
of not doing that?
I didn't like it
when I went through it.
But,
I'm so glad
for the fruit
that it produced in me
that I could then
reproduce
in the children
that God asked me
to steward.
There is this,
this connection.
And,
the goal is,
is fruit that remains.
Filled,
my,
some of the fruit
that I see in my children,
I mean,
when I get a hold
of God's superintending
in my life
to bring me to the place
and my wife to the place
where we could impart
that to them
and see them actually
walk it out,
I don't know
if it's a result
or a Holy Spirit thing,
it's probably all mixed,
but there is
inexpressible
and glorious joy.
And all that,
well,
I won't say junk,
all the slight
unfortunate things,
Mom.
I'm glad for.
So,
I know it's
Apple Blossom
and I know
it's the Sunday
on Apple Blossom,
but you do know
that today
actually a third
of worldwide Christendom
celebrates as Easter.
The Orthodox Church
sees this as Easter.
And actually,
this whole season
of formation stuff
we've been doing
has been during
the Eastern Orthodox
Lent period.
Now,
we didn't want to tell you
that we're going to run you
through a second Lent.
We didn't want to do that to you.
So we just did it
without telling you.
But today
is about the next season.
Today,
by the way,
for those of you
who are wondering,
it's very rare
that there's so much
distance between
one and the other.
The Eastern Orthodox Church,
so everyone followed
the Julian calendar
up until about
the 1500s.
And then Gregory,
Pope of the
Western Church,
he decided that,
you know what,
it's time to get
with the times.
Because scientists
didn't quite have
calendars right,
and so they fixed
the calendar
and named it
after himself,
Gregorian calendar,
which I think is a riot.
Because I'm sure
he didn't come up with it.
And the Eastern Orthodox,
and they said,
okay,
so now we're going to
figure Easter
off the moon
that fits with
the correct calendar.
And the Eastern Orthodox Church
said,
hey, look,
the Julian calendar
was good enough for Jesus,
it's good enough for us.
It was settled back
in Nicaea,
and so they just keep
this other count.
Now,
for civil purposes,
everyone's on
the Julian calendar.
Well, not everyone,
Nepal's not,
but everyone else
was on it.
But for the religious purpose,
they're on this
Eastern calendar.
And so I think
this is a wonderful time
to begin to think
about the resurrection.
And the resurrection
as it relates
to ourselves
and the seasons
of formation
that God
likes to walk us through.
I don't know
what season
you're in,
but there's
a next season.
Your worst day
is not your last day.
By the way,
your best day
might not be
your last day either.
If you're in silence,
God will speak again.
If you're in the desert,
you'll find an oasis.
If you're in darkness,
let God finish his work
so that you might
enter that next season.
My own dark night
of the soul,
I didn't know
if I was going
to survive ministry.
And I can tell you
that God has been
gracious and kind.
And interestingly,
he hasn't answered
all the questions
that just drove me
into it.
He just didn't answer them.
But he showed up.
And somehow
his presence
is enough
in the midst
of my confusion.
When I can't put
a dot
or a cross
above every
T and I,
but I know
he's there.
It's kind of like,
you know,
the story about
the guy
who was applying
to be fire chief.
And they were asking
all the firemen,
which resume
do you want?
And they were looking
at the resumes,
schooling,
and they finally said,
one guy said,
you know what?
I don't care
about any of that.
All I want to know,
has he felt the flames
and inhaled the smoke?
Has he been there?
So,
let's look at this
John chapter.
And then,
after we look
at John 16,
and if you have a Bible,
go ahead and turn it on
or open it up there.
I'm just going to walk
through this John 16.
Same passage
that you all
appropriately applauded for.
No, Donovan,
they weren't applauding you.
It was the Bible.
Although you're worthy
of being applauded,
you're awesome.
You're great.
Verse 16,
Jesus went on to say,
in a little while,
you will see me no more.
And then after a little while,
you will see me.
Okay.
At this,
some of the disciples
said to one another,
what does he mean
by saying,
in a little while,
you will see me no more?
And then after a little while,
you'll see me.
And apparently,
he was also saying,
because I'm going
to the Father.
So,
what's he talking about?
Jesus is,
from chapter 13
through all the way
until the Garden of Gethsemane
and his actual crucifixion,
his betrayal,
his crucifixion,
his resurrection,
he's,
it's kind of like
the last minute
download of everything
they need to know,
13 and 14 and 15
and 16 and 17
and in 17
he prays for him
and he's trying to,
I'm going
and I want you guys to,
I mean,
I've been teaching this
to you for three years
but obviously,
you haven't remembered it.
So,
let me try again.
he's talking about
what's going to happen
and they're,
they're clueless.
They kept asking,
what does he mean
by a little while?
We don't understand
what he's saying.
And Jesus thought
that they wanted
to ask him about this
and so he said to them,
so in other words,
Jesus is on to point three
in his lecture
and they're back
at point one.
What's he talking about?
And as being a good teacher,
he noticed his audience,
he goes,
ah,
okay,
let's go back there.
Are you still asking
one another
what I meant
when I said
in a little while
you will see me no more
and then after a little while
you will see me?
Very truly,
and now notice this,
I tell you,
you will weep
and mourn
while the world rejoices.
You will grieve,
but your grief,
and it doesn't say
will be replaced
by joy,
but your grief
will turn into joy.
That God,
just like when you got saved,
he transformed you.
That God will take
your grief
and he will create
a metamorphosis
of your very grief
to be able to bring joy
into your life.
Then verse 21,
he tries to give an illustration
so that they'd understand it.
A woman giving birth
to a child
has pain
because her time has come.
I remember watching a movie
with my mother one time
and I was young,
I was, I don't know,
14, 13, 12, something,
and the woman
was giving birth
to a baby
and there were people
gathered around her
and she's like,
ah, ah,
there's sweat pouring down,
you know,
and my mom goes,
that is so ridiculous.
And I'm like,
what?
It hurts more than that.
And I thought,
glad I'm a man.
A woman giving birth
to a child has pain
because her time has come
but when her baby is born
she forgets the anguish
because of her joy
that a child is born
into the world.
And then someone has said,
and I didn't write down
who it was
but I really like it.
The baby doesn't come
after the labor pains.
The baby comes by means
of the labor pains.
Because every resurrection
is preceded by a death.
The power to know
the power of his resurrection
will have a component
of the fellowship
of his sufferings
if we really want
to know Christ.
Remember I read earlier,
God's desire
is inexpressible
and glorious joy
for you.
When God wants
to disembed
our childish ways
that are just
ingrained in us,
rarely is it easy
or pain-free.
So when I was a kid
in elementary school,
we were playing kickball
and we were playing
out on the playground
blacktop
and the teacher
obviously hadn't
done this before
because she brought out
orange cones
as bases.
Now, orange cones
are great
for like boundaries
of goals
or boundaries
on the side.
But, you know,
I booted that ball
out into right field
and I went running
and I touched
first base
second base
and as I'm running
to third base,
you know,
I don't know,
nine?
As I'm running
to third base,
I can tell the ball's coming.
And so I got to beat it there
but you don't want
to overrun the base
and so I leap
to the base
and I land
about the middle
of that orange cone
which the cone
then collapses
which then my ankle
and I go flying,
my momentum carries me
over the cone
and when I land,
it kind of hurts
and I get up
and I look at my hand
and my pinky
goes out a little bit
and then it goes
straight up
and then it went
that way.
Well,
it didn't hurt
at the moment.
I'm looking
and I'm going,
wow,
that's weird
and they just
tagged me out
so I was bummed
about that
and then the third
baseman said,
oh,
I think you're
supposed to pull it
and so I grabbed
my pinky
and I pulled it
and it was
straight again.
Okay,
that's cool.
Well,
then they sent me,
I mean,
the teacher had seen it.
She quickly picked up
the bases
and put something
else down there
but she sent me
down to the nurse
and by the time
I got to the nurse,
the nurse just touched it
and I mean,
excruciating pain.
I mean,
just blowing on it
and it hurt
and of course,
you know,
she touched it,
she saw how much it hurt,
I told her what happened
and she called my mom,
my mom came,
we went to the doctor,
the doctor x-rayed it
and the doctor said to me,
Matt,
if that ever happens again,
don't pull it.
He said,
there's so many things
you can do wrong.
He said,
but you got really lucky
because when you pulled it,
you said it
and it was right
and you didn't have
to do anything.
Now,
here's my question.
Oh,
a couple questions.
Can you imagine
if I had not pulled it
and I'd walk to the nurse
and we got in the car
and we'd gone to the doctor,
he wouldn't really have
to x-ray it at that point,
but he would x-ray it
because he's got
to get it set right.
Can you imagine,
first of all,
how much that would hurt?
Can you imagine
if he said,
oh,
Matt,
man,
that's going to really hurt you.
I think we'll leave it
like it is.
Would you want a God
who said,
I'm sorry,
that's going to really hurt.
We'll just leave it
like it is.
I look at my pinky now
and I have inexpressible
and glorious joy.
Actually,
when my strength
to weight ratio
was better,
I used to be
a pretty good rock climber
and I liked that pinky.
I am so glad
that it got fixed.
Verse 22 of this passage
ends with this promise
from Jesus
that you're not going
to see me
and you're going
and I know
this is talking
about immediate
three days
crucifixion,
resurrection,
but it's also
a metaphorical picture
of what happens
in our life
during those times
that we do not see him
and we see him again.
But here's the outcome
at the end
of verse 22.
No one
will take your joy away.
Parker Palmer,
an orthodox,
I'm sorry,
a Quaker,
theologian,
educator,
writer,
he writes this.
He says,
emerging from,
quote,
the midst
of the dark
woods
of depression,
he found a poem
taking form
within himself.
It's titled
Harrowing.
The plow
has savaged
this sweet field.
Misshapen
clods
of earth
kicked up,
rocks
are twisted
and roots
exposed to view.
Last year's growth
demolished
by the blade,
I have plowed
my life this way,
turned over
a whole history,
looking for the roots
of what went
wrong
until my face
is ravaged
and furrowed
and scarred.
Enough!
The job
is done.
Whatever's been
uprooted,
let it be.
Seedbed
for the growing
that is to come.
I plowed
to unearth
last year's reasons.
The farmer
plows
to plant
a growing
season.
Folks,
I don't know
what season
you're in,
but God
does have
another season
for you.
Trust in
his goodness.
The seasons
of formation
about this
simple thing,
we believe
that God
is good.
Regardless
of what we see,
regardless
of what we
experience,
regardless
of how it
comes,
by faith
we say,
no,
God is
good.
And God
keeps his
word.
And no one
will take
your joy
away.